

Teemu Daniel Laajala FICAN Cancer Researcher



b. 1987



Turku, Finland



(+358) 400 842 893



http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7016-7354



teelaa@utu.fi teemu.daniel.laajala@gmail.com

### Scientific focus —

- Applied math & machine learning
- Prognostic & predictive modeling
- Preclinical & clinical oncology
- Multi-'omics & translatability
- Open science, data, and source code
- R-programming & CRAN-packages

#### Other skills -

ΙT

- R, C#, Python, Java, C, Matlab
- · LaTeX, SQL, XML, JSON
- MS Office, Inkscape, GIMP, Adobe suite, HTML/CSS

## Languages

· Professional: Finnish & English

· Conversational: Swedish

### Linked profiles

- ResearchGate
- Google Scholar
- Stack Overflow
- GitHub
- LinkedIn
- Twitter

## Research experience

2018 –	FICAN West (Läntinen Syöpäkeskus, UTU)	Post-doc
2018 –	University of Colorado – Costello Lab (UCDenver)	Post-doc
2013 – 2018	Department of Mathematics & Statistics (UTU)	PhD student
	Multiple research topics mainly focused on oncology	

with a PhD thesis focus on advanced prostate cancer.

2013 – 2018 Turku Centre for Biotechnology (UTU, ÅA)

PhD student
PSA-molecule research and models for predicting
progression of prostate and kidney cancer.

2013 – 2018 Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland (FIMM, HY) Project researcher Head bioinformatician in multiple collaborative projects.

2010 – 2012 Department of Mathematics & Statistics (UTU) Project researcher ChIP-seg method development and analysis of cancer studies.

2008, 2009 Turku Centre for Biotechnology (UTU, ÅA) Summer intern ChIP-seq sequence and diabetes microarray analyses.

## Education

2013 – 2018 PhD ('with honours' special mention)

Topic of thesis: Modeling and Prediction
of Advanced Prostate Cancer

University of Turku

2006 – 2012 MSc (Tech) (Bioinformatics, 'exceptional' honors)

Aalto University

## Selected publications (First or shared first author)

#### IF 2017/2018

5.481	Laajala TD*, Murtojärvi M*, et al. <i>ePCR: an R-package for survival and</i>
	time-to-event prediction in advanced prostate cancer, applied to real-
	world patient cohorts. Bioinformatics. 2018 Nov 15;34(22):3957-
	3959.
4.540	Huvila J*, Laajala TD*, et al. Combined ASRGL1 and p53 immunohis-
	tochemistry as an independent predictor of survival in endometrioid
	endometrial carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol. 2018 Apr;149(1):173-180.
36.421	Guinney J*, Wang T*, Laajala TD*, et al. Prediction of overall survival

Guinney J\*, Wang T\*, Laajala TD\*, et al. Prediction of overall survival for patients with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer: development of a prognostic model through a crowdsourced challenge with open clinical trial data. Lancet Oncol. 2017 Jan;18(1):132-142. Laajala TD, et al. Optimized design and analysis of preclinical inter-

4.122 Laajala TD, et al. *Optimized design and analysis of preclinical inter vention studies in vivo.* Sci Rep. 2016 Aug 2;6:30723.

10.199 Laajala TD, et al. Improved statistical modeling of tumor growth and treatment effect in preclinical animal studies with highly heterogeneous responses in vivo. Clin Cancer Res. 2012 Aug 15;18(16):4385-96.

\* = Equal contribution

# Researcher

#### Awards & Funding

Participation in two DREAM challenges with DREAM 9.5 mCRPC Challenge Top Performer (2015) & DREAM Anti-PD1 Response Prediction DREAM Challenge Top Performer (2021, ongoing). Elias Tillandz -prize 2017 (best scientific publication in Turku BioCity) as first author; again in 2019 as non-first author.

FICAN Cancer Researcher (Finnish Cancer Institute, 2020-2022); NIH grant "Curated prostate cancer data for novel and reproducible prognostic modeling" (2020-2022); Finnish Cultural Foundation (central fund 2014, VS-regional 2018, 2019); DRDP doctoral programme (2014); NIH/NCI DREAM/mCRPC-sponsorship (2016).

## Overview

Brief statistics 10/2021: Citations 1014 & h index 20 (Google Scholar); ResearchGate score 33.41 (best >10% quantile); 30+ peer-reviewed articles in PubMed, of which 5+ in >10 IF journals; Stack Overflow best >25% quantile, >3% quantile in R.